hello everybody so
today we're going to talk about the free
energy principle
and how it relates to psychedelics which
is a very
very exciting topic there's a lot of
excitement i think in the
academic community about this topic i've
got to say
i'm going to present three completely
new ideas
uh well two of them have been kind of
like talked about in various qri
uh articles as well as videos uh there's
one completely new one
but uh in either case uh these ideas um
you know like is they're not being
talked about in the academic literature
we intend to
to publish them and run simulations but
for in the meantime it's just like very
exciting kind of like these new
perspectives on
how psychedelics and the free energy
previous people relate to each other
and as you know kind of the north star
of this conversation we will have
the basically the goal of explaining
indra's net in terms of
the free energy principle which i think
it's actually possible
so so let's get to it so
first the quality of the day is indra's
net so you know it is said in in various
uh yeah eastern
israel philosophies that uh you know
indra is very powerful god basically has
this net uh hanging on kind of like
the ceiling and you know one of the
palaces in the in the realms of the gods
and
uh you know each of the nodes of the net
is a
you know multi-dimensional gem at this
beautiful beautiful gem
and the net is infinite it's completely
infinite and
what happens is that each of those
gems will contain a reflection a tiny
reflection
of every other gem and then within the
reflection and
of every other gem you will find an even
tinier
reflection of every other gem and so on
at infinitum you know i mean of course
if this was physically realized it would
be a limit you know because
you know uh photons are quantized
ultimately right so there's not going to
be like
infinite resolution when you observe it
and and you try to find kind of the
world in
in a grain of sand so to speak um but uh
but yeah it's a very interesting and
powerful metaphor
and um you know it's used
methodologically to kind of like talk
about the
interdependence of everything on
everything else uh kind of in buddhism
and and even hinduism and
um and that's a powerful kind of like
vision i like a like
imagine you know if you assume that
that's the case
that you know like everything in the
world actually stands in kind of an
indra where internet relationship to
everything else
and everything implies each other like
even like a piece of
trash or like a piece of i don't know
this foam i don't know it was a random
thing that uh
came in in a package of essential oils
like this
is interdependent with absolutely
everything else uh and more so you know
this is the
final product of its backwards light
cone which you know contains
such a huge amount of uh you know every
like the cosmic background radiation and
well everything is interpret
interdependent with everything else
now that's kind of a mind-blowing idea
um
but what's the what's the use of it and
you know
recently uh there's kind of this um uh
fascinating dharma teacher
uh rob burbia i've been uh consuming a
lot of his lectures
he has this book called seeing that
freeze
and one of the things that he talks
about is how in a sense you can
interpret
inside practice uh as opposed to for
example like concentration practice
or morality practice you know just
inside practicing in the buddhist
meditation
as basically ways of seeing the world
that reduce suffering that diminish the
dukkha
the the the unpleasant qualities of
experience uh so for example like being
hyper
hyper aware or like being in the moment
or
perceiving things as like empty of
inherent existence
when you apply those ways of seeing
to even like you know unpleasant
low-level body sensations
for a number of people in a number of
circumstances it can have
a great reduction in their suffering now
it doesn't always work and it's
really interesting to see like way why
does it work and under what
circumstances does it work
but uh as kind of like as a general
frame i really like it
it's very very pragmatic it's kind of
like oh these deep quote-unquote
esoteric
views of the world you know
interdependence and uh
you know dependent origination and uh
emptiness and all of that stuff
um ultimately you know they're not
necessarily
uh useful because they're fundamentally
true
maybe you know as buddha might say like
it's unknowable
ultimately but internalizing those ways
of seeing
the world and your experience lessens
the suffering allows you to kind of like
drop a lot of
baggage that carries around and causes
dissonances internally
and kind of like cleans your experience
and i think a powerful experiences of
indra's web
well it actually depends on how you
interpret them because there's also kind
of a spiritual materialism
um risk of it like if you experience
like a mind blowing like meditation or
lsd state of you know everything
reflecting everything else
and you think like oh my gosh i'm
enlightened like i'm one with everything
like kind of like now maybe you have
even more baggage because you kind of
have like this
self-conception uh that arose out of
that
but there's also you know kind of the
flip side which is like maybe actually
understanding the
dependence of everything with everything
else allows you to lessen the amount of
fabrications
that you uh essentially engage with
especially mindless fabrications because
in a sense you
you recognize their empty essence and
they're
co-arising with everything else and in a
sense you can
treat them by modifying the conditions
gonna give rise to them anyway so
uh interest web not only is it a
mind-blowing experience
it's also potentially like very
pragmatically useful in that it might
lessen your suffering to some extent
uh now importantly too i think it is
very valuable to study as an experience
itself and uh you know like different
experiences have like different degrees
of like how much they are like indra's
net um now because
you know at qri we essentially assume
indirect realism about perception
uh basically yeah when you're having
like an experience of indra's web i
don't think
you're literally you know contacting the
rest of the cosmos and seeing how
everything reflects everything else
i think what's going on is you're
instantiating a state of consciousness
that essentially has this fascinating
property that every part of that state
of consciousness in some
tricky but non-trivial and very real
sense is actually reflecting every other
part of the experience
and that is what i will explain
with the free energy principle so
exciting isn't it
i should also remark that uh because of
the symmetry theory valence i mean most
of the intro
interest net kind of experiences tend to
be pretty fractal and like highly
detailed
but above all very constant and very
symmetrical so
they tend to be extremely blissful so
again a lot of people may experience
interest net and uh kind of like be
fascinated by it
but not recognizing where the valence
comes from you know they may think that
the valence comes from
literally becoming embedded into the
fabric of reality
but you know that's kind of a tyranny of
the intentional object
it's kind of like in a sense it's like
reading too much into the intentional
content of the experience so i would say
rather what i would kind of advise you
to do
is to pay attention to the way in which
those patterns are either consonant or
dissonant with one another and the claim
is that you know blissful
indras net experiences for the most part
will basically be hyper harmonious
there's going to be hyper harmony
they're going to be minimizing
dissonance in a in a very very deep way
so so that's the the quality of the day
uh highly recommended uh you can get it
with meditation it's very common on dmt
as we'll talk about
uh and it may be freeing in some some
deep sense that i think is very valuable
um okay so now let's get on to the topic
of the day which is uh the free energy
principle
more concretely and uh there's a couple
things to say you know
i mean first of all like carl friesen's
free energy principle
and predictive coding as you know
paradigm
which are slightly different things and
the free energy principle can derive the
predictive coding and maybe not the
other way around but they're very
interrelated
and they're part of the lineages of qri
so basically we have now ten lineages
uh that basically we draw a lot of
inspiration and theoretical frameworks
from
uh lenses that we use to understand the
world and we also have our own lenses
for example
neural annealing and the symmetry theory
of valence and a bunch of other
stuff like the tyranny of intentional
object and so on
um which are ours i mean we've been
developing them for the last
i don't know seven years or so uh it's
been a big effort
and uh hopefully we will actually be
able to you know present
all of that in a very formal fashion all
of those developments with their
predictions and
testing those predictions and so on but
yeah i mean current doesn't exist in a
vacuum it very
very much exists in the context that
these
other lineages generate and a very
important lineage
they're all very important so
[Laughter]
one of those lineages is a free energy
principle um
so it's very important for qri i i would
also mention
that um uh you know quentin freirecks uh
you know the the the lead engineer at
qri uh actually presented about nero
annealing to
carl friesen and his lab and uh you know
we got a lot of really interesting
feedback mostly extremely positive
feedback
uh very encouraging and basically they
were suggesting that we publish
a particular version of what we're
working on
and um so that is you know in the works
and uh i'm very excited about that
okay so let's get into the actual
content of it okay so
the free energy principle is one of
those kind of like
really high level cool ideas
that in a sense as you munch on
it you start to see it everywhere
and i would compare it with like a
couple other kind of things in that
kind of category or like very high level
interpretations of reality that
everything kind of like like gives you a
completely new lens on reality
one of them for example is uh evolution
you know this idea that
whenever you have um reproduction with
selection and variation
you will have basically the the
ingredients
for evolution now that is a
fascinating you know clever idea kind of
like synthesizing
evolution to just those three principles
and when you have those three principles
you
will start seeing evolution everywhere
you know not only biological evolution
but like all over the place
you know in in uh consequences game of
life
in you know fundamental particles in it
will show up everywhere
um but you can maybe even distill it
further
you know you can say like well that's
maybe a special case of something more
deep
so what could be that that that thing
that is uh kind of like even deeper
well maybe it is the survival of the
stable
and the survival of the stable is kind
of this meta principle rather like
from it you can essentially derive
you know the three principles of
evolution and it's kind of like a deeper
deeper truth you know that like yes sure
there's like biological organisms and
all that but
you know if a rock is really stable you
know it will be here it will be around
like it
if it has like mechanisms to continue to
exist you know that's what exists what
exists
is what is good at being stable
in some in some way you know something
could be very variable it could be a
dynamic system
but maybe construed as the state space
of the entire system that
is a very stable construct you know and
i would say that yeah
biological organisms are like that
they're very dynamic but in some sense
they do carry some
stable kind of a metadata and and that
is
what is actually you know is immortal
you know our genes
are immortal over the generations even
if the individual isn't you know and in
that sense
survival of the stable is kind of a meta
principle i would also say you know
you know bayesian epistemology is like
maybe one of these like pretty
pretty high level concepts that allows
you to reinterpret so many things
that like for example like once you
understand that hey
the brain is receiving information from
its environment in a time series fashion
i mean there's massive parallelism but
there's also time
you know we're embedded in time so the
information that we get
is that happens over time it's time
series and whenever you have kind of
like that data structure
and you're trying to minimize you know
prediction errors
it follows from math that you're going
to be doing
bayesian inference and there's no way
around it i mean that's just a hard
constraint and it doesn't matter if the
brain is made of like
neurons or you know it's made of like
honey and
and bees or you know if it's made of the
population of china or whatnot
like if it's making accurate predictions
about time series data structures
it is going to be you know making
bayesian inference you know that's
that's just a super hard constraint
now bayesian inference is something that
leaves at the computational level
you still need to dig deeper into the
algorithmic and that implementation
level as i've talked about in
other videos go to the digital uh
digital sentience video for a deep
discussion about this but yeah in a
sense computational level
uh doesn't really tell you the full
story but it is a constraint you know
it's kind of a boundary condition
upon which everything else has to be fit
and for sure you know
nervous systems do bayesian inference
period you know that's
that's a hard constraint they have to be
otherwise they wouldn't actually be able
to make
accurate predictions now the free energy
principle
some could even think kind of brings
together
all of these high level paradigms maybe
into like an even bigger
higher level paradigm which is which is
crazy and
uh you know at qri we have a lot of
respect in general for
thinkers who are what
mike calls one true ontologists
you know who who kind of like take one
principle or one set of ideas
and and try to basically apply it to all
of reality
and and see how far that goes and okay
maybe it doesn't apply to all
reality but in the process of trying to
apply it everywhere
you discover a lot of things and you may
be able to massively compress
a lot of you know crazy highly detailed
information reality with just
one one principle and the free energy
principle may do that
uh so briefly stated and i'll go into
like more detail
essentially it says that any dynamic
system
that is actually capable
of surviving is actually able to
sustain itself must be able
to in a sense minimize the entropy is
receiving from its environment
right so uh you have like a
a little cat and uh if it's kind of a
just always going towards you know the
absolutely most chaotic environments
possible
uh you know it's going to die you know
like it's going to go to the oven or
it's going to
i don't know bad images but uh the point
is that like
if you're like maximizing chaos
that chaos is going to eat you yeah so
basically it's going to shake you apart
uh so systems that actually do survive
that actually are
stable as i was talking about a skin is
like this generator for the you know
theory of evolution are basically those
that are able to minimize the amount of
entropy
um unexpected entropy that the
environment basically imposes on
on them and from that
through a chain of inferences you can
arrive at the implication the dynamic
systems that survive
in the universe have to on
some level have an internal
model or representation of their
environment such that they can
anticipate what is going to happen to
them
given the particular input that they are
receiving and
basically avoid states of very high
entropy as a consequence
so um it's kind of crazy right like
the the thing is like this may apply to
a lot of like systems that are you know
counterintuitive like
you know one thing is uh is the brain
we're like okay we kind of intuitively
intuitively understand that yes we do
have kind of an inner model of the of
the environment
uh but this may also apply to other
things like you know like a
a wheel uh on on water or
or like a tornado or like other other
dynamic systems like that you know
convection
currents and things like that that like
implicitly
you know maybe not explicitly i'm not
being that saying that
convention currents actually contain
kind of like a a picture of their
environment inside them but
implicitly they must be doing some
some level of computational processing
that is in a sense uh
making them maximally adapted to their
environment and uh
now there's like kind of various schools
within you know the free energy
principle literature of like okay are
are the
the the representations uh explicit or
implicit and like maybe that depends on
the particular system that we're talking
about and
you know i think most people would
generally agree that like at least the
brain is making explicit representations
so it's not you know we're not just
convection currents like there's
uh something more explicitly
computational going on
but at the same time it must be
satisfying kind of this principle that
if it's going to survive it has to
actually be able to predict this
environment
now the the the actual term um
uh a free energy is an information
theoretic construct
uh so it's not a physical construct it's
an information theoretical construct
that bounce evidence for a model of data
so
here's the thing like if you have
complete information about the world
and uh the inner latent states basically
the the latent parameters
that give rise give us rise to what's
happening in the world
um you could in a sense like compute
how surprising a particular set of input
is
and in that sense like we would actually
be talking about the
surprise minimization principle as
opposed to the free energy principle
so why are we talking about the free
energy principle instead and what is
this free energy
well it's an information theoretical
construct it's not
free it's not energy in the physical
sense although
as i'll mention in a moment there might
be an isomorphism in some circumstances
but uh free energy appears basically in
machine learning and statistics
you know i have like this book for
example of uh deep learning
and uh you know in page 625
you have this definition of variational
free energy
uh which is essentially um the point is
that
yeah i think like here is the
variational free energy and essentially
the the point is that
um this provides an upper
bound to how surprising
the stimuli is given your generative
model of the world
i know these are these are a lot of
words and uh you know to do justice to
this uh topic
it would take many hours and actually a
detailed presentation with uh
definitions and
all the math in there but uh what you
have to know right now is that
you know the like the variational free
energy is an
upper bound on the true surprise
that uh that a particular stimuli is
generating um and surprise here means
that basically the model says that these
are very unlikely
events so there's information very
construct like the negative of the log
surprise basically provides kind of this
uh
total surprisal of the stimuli and that
is what you should be minimizing
you don't have access to that it's
intractable so instead what you can do
is try to minimize free energy which is
an
upper bound that is tractable and is
computable
and is essentially something that yeah
in machine learning is used routinely uh
to to basically uh optimize uh
inferential learning in probabilistic
graphical models again apologies for all
of the
all of the jargon uh but you have to
what you have to get is that
uh this is a clever and tractable way
of minimizing how surprising the stimuli
are from the environment um
uh there's a couple of things to mention
here is like okay if somebody might
claim that
uh if you're minimizing surprise why
don't you just go to a dark room that's
kind of the kodako dark room
uh interpretation well uh yeah because
you know if you're
in a dark room everything is infinitely
predictable you know like you know
exactly what you're going to
be getting uh and that in principle
should you know make you feel great
because you're minimizing the prediction
errors that you're getting
well not quite because actually the
model
that we have of the world is dynamic
and the things that are expected in that
model
are sequences of events um so actually
there's no kind of like
you know local maxima that is kind of
like oh you know this homogeneous
perfectly
you know symmetrical state is like you
know
maximally expected you know because your
model actually goes against it
it actually says no like that would be
very unexpected you know you don't
expect to wake up in the morning
and just see nothing and have no sense
or input that's an incredibly surprising
state
right so actually going into dark room
and becoming super thirsty and not
eating and so on
that's a drastically increases
your surprise and your free energy so
actually in a sense like
minimizing free energy it does entail
kind of like doing a lot of very
very simple quotidian like normal
everyday things
that in a sense restrict the
range of states that you find in because
and that's an important implication too
uh you're trying to minimize the entropy
of the
uh density of uh of states that you can
uh
you can inhabit internally because that
in a sense
uh will maximize your chances of
continuing to exist
existing definitely and um and uh yeah i
mean as a consequence yes if you all of
a sudden
sort of find yourself in a dark room
maybe on a low level you could think
that's you know very
surprised very uh there's no prediction
errors because it's constant
at the same time you will be making the
inference that you're probably in huge
danger
so in that sense yes actually it doesn't
minimize free energy
the other fascinating thing about this
is um
active inference that in a sense there's
two ways in which you can minimize the
free energy
a you can change your model you know
you're getting something very very
surprising
in order to minimize the free energy
that that is generating
you can change your model
such that what you're experiencing now
becomes less surprising
and that's one way um
but we also require uh basically
a balance between the accuracy and the
complexity of the model because you
shouldn't over feed
so basically there's only so far you uh
basically a free energy minimizing
system
will be willing to in a sense adjust its
model to the immediate
uh immediate information because it's
also taking into account all of the
previous information and like you know
that that shouldn't be discarded if it's
actually an embodied entity
is gonna survive you know new
information could be garbage so like you
really can't
update too heavily on it and uh also
that gives
you know brings us to the topic of uh
the precision on the high level priors
of the model
which is that yes i mean like um very
surprising things may not actually
uh be warrant deeply updating the model
precisely because you have way too much
evidence in the past
that like yeah most likely maybe the
input that you're getting is like
spurious or something and you can maybe
as a constant you know spin up an
additional model
that is about like okay what is the
probability that data is noisy or faulty
and like then you start to model
under what circumstances data becomes
faulty and that becomes the way in which
you minimize free energy
not just instantly updating your model
and the other thing
though is that it will be
the other way of minimizing free energy
is to actually
act on the world such that you actually
make the inputs
later on more expected so that's kind of
like
yeah basically you're like close to a
hot stub or like you know i don't know
like a
a very very chaotic bar where there's
like about to
enough a bar fight is about to to be to
break and like there's a bunch of drunk
people
it's very chaotic you know one that's
just going to generate a ton of you know
free energy for you
uh for you to minimize it with something
you can do is kind of like start walking
and getting out of the bar
and you will be outside it's gonna be a
way more predictable environment
so there you go you know like action
onwards you know
that can also be a method to to reduce
the free energy and so in the end
what you get with this theory is kind of
this beautiful interpretation of you
know dynamic systems that survive
including humans
that they will be kind of like in a in a
balanced
way uh modifying their internal models
and also acting on the world
so that there's fewer prediction errors
and that as a consequence you know what
we are doing right now is kind of uh
doing that implicitly on some level
you know uh another thing to mention is
this concept of the markov blanket
which is basically in probabilistic
graphical models
um you should look that up if you're
curious uh basically you can define
this notion of a barrier between an
inside and an outside which is basically
um for a given set of nodes you can look
at
all of the nodes that in a sense if you
wear to
to kind of like uh uh uh fix them
they would in a sense like lock in the
information that their internal nodes
can get from their environment
in a way it's kind of like the market
blocket is the outer shell of a
particular set of
probabilistic graphical models nodes and
uh
and in that sense they generate an
inside and an outside and
what the free energy principle will
entail
is that whenever you have a markov
blanket
and you know those are the and it's
modeling a dynamic system
it will be the case that the free energy
principle will apply
for that markov blanket and you know in
actual something like you know bayesian
predictive coding
models where you have a hierarchy
of um kind of like models that go from
a very low kind of like sensory data to
like very high level kind of like
notions of the self and so on
that in a sense there's going to be this
kind of quasi-concentric shells
configuration where each of the kind of
layers
is going to try to predict and
anticipate and modify
the one right underneath and in a sense
the process of model building and world
building of creating the the world
simulation that you inhabit in this
paradigm
is what arises out of the kind of like
tug tug of war or competition between
all of these
various shells trying to predict each
other
and the the end result of that is
a hierarchical model that in a sense
encodes information about the world in a
uh
more and more refined way and uh a more
and more abstract way
as you go go in now of course there's a
huge debate on like whether
a model like that actually fits what
happened you know what's going on in the
brain
of course there's like some degree to
which
you can model um uh the layers of the
cortex for example
in kind of like this hierarchical way
you know for v and then like v1 v2 and
so on
at the same time the brain is like
really interconnected you know and
there's like
connections between layer one and layer
five and
and it's kind of like very very mixed up
in a sense so
uh identifying the mark of blankets of
the neural networks of the brain is not
as easy uh
as kind of like just dividing into
layers uh there's more
complication to it and also you know
down the line
you know at qri we actually you know
believe that consciousness is a holistic
field behavior
um uh rather is a is a utilizes holistic
field behavior and that's the
reason why it was selected by natural
selection
and recruited by natural selection for
computation so
actually consciousness might be
inherently extremely interconnected by
its very nature and so
within a moment of experience there may
actually not be like an
easy or even conceivably possible way of
generating markov blankets
so that might be kind of a something
that you know runs deep against
some of the core assumptions of the free
energy principle at the same time
i do think that it is quite possible
um to uh make approximate
markov blankets within your your world
simulation and that alone
you know allows us to basically use the
free energy principle as a lens we will
recognize that it's an imperfect lens
because these are partly kind of
imperfect markup blankets there's
leakage of information between the
inside and
outside but uh it's gonna be good it can
be still being insightful
okay so that's that that's uh the free
energy principle so now let's go
to apply it to psychedelics and i mean
the ver
first thing i'll mention is uh rebus
which is reduced the beliefs under
uh psychedelics uh a paper by robin
carhart harris and carl freestone
and uh and it's fascinating basically
what they argue
is that um
the net effect of psychedelics
in your world model is
weakening the precision of the high
level priors
uh meaning that like these very high
level priors very kind of like central
uh you know innermost layers of the mark
of blankets
that those in a sense become uh
less strong they don't impose
on all of the other layers as much
they're kind of like weaker
they're reduced and uh and as such
it allows bottom-up information to
propagate across the hierarchy
and give rise to bigger belief
updates so that's that's a very very big
fascinating
idea and then they justify it based on
neurophysiology in particular they
they you know examine the hypotheses
that deep
pyramidal neurons are encoding these
very high level priors
and that the first d2a receptor um
basically uh is a way in which these
neurons can be sensitized
and because they basically can receive
a stimulation from like lower layers of
the hierarchy
um when they are sensitized that as an
implication gives rise to basically
a more straightforward information
propagation
between the lower layers and the higher
layers and
well there's a bunch of speculation also
on like okay maybe
the way the the priors are implemented
are through basically
uh patterns of synchrony in those like
top layer neurons
and that you know this kind of
sensitization and and bottom-up
information propagation
gives rise to basically the the
desynchronization of them so you get a
kind of like rather than a
coherent story kind of a imparting you
know
a synchronized top level prior it's kind
of like competing
you know maybe patterns of synchrony uh
they're kind of like
all of them trying to kind of like make
sense of the world and
make sense of each other and uh it's
kind of like
an anarchy i mean the robin carhart
harris talks about it
as the anarchic brain that now you have
kind of all of these different
yeah basically clusters and components
of the model that are in a sense
yeah giving rise to bottom-up updates on
the belief network
and these you know in terms of
aesthetics of science this is pretty
cool
uh uh there's this fascinating book uh
by paul
feyerabend i don't know how to pronounce
his name but um
uh it's called against method and he's
talking about yeah basically this uh
uh the idyllic picture of the scientific
method
as a recipe that you just follow that
yeah that doesn't work and a really good
quip
that comes from that book is this idea
that
facts dictate theory
as much as theory dictates facts or
maybe put the other way
for a stronger effect you know theory
dictates what facts
are as much as the facts dictate what
theory is
so in a sense like this is why like
paradigms take such a long time
to advance in science you know because
like uh
whenever a paradigm explains a lot of
information which usually yeah i mean
good scientific paradigms will do that
and you bring up you know a new study or
something that like
provides counter evidence uh to it
like a strong strong counter evidence to
it
the typical response is to basically
reinterpret those facts
in order for them to fit the theory
rather than like re-examine the theory
which is a much bigger enterprise to do
and plus there's some vested interest in
academia and so on which i'm not gonna
get into that
but yeah i mean basically um uh facts
dictate theory as much as the theory
dictates facts and um
and in a sense with rebus the really
cool thing
right is like you can imagine that
happening in your own brain
that you are um
interpreting the world through your
narrow lenses and maybe
you know by the age of 30 those narrow
lenses are pretty crystallized and like
if they're
bad models of the world like uh
it might be good to in a sense gonna
revise them and allow
you know low level prediction errors to
actually propagate all the way upwards
so that you update your model and that's
kind of like the
the ideal use in therapy of psychedelics
given that particular
reading on what psychedelics do which is
in a sense you allow people to kind of
get
unstuck prevent the default mode network
or whatever you know story we might want
to tell here
uh from just imposing its high level
priors
with very high precision everywhere and
instead be open to actually update
it's uh it's prior is based on new
information even if it's information you
have stored inside
so like in the rebus paper they also
talk about like it's not only kind of
prediction errors from the
environment it's also kind of like
sensitizing to like
oscillations in the limbic system you
know so like emotions that maybe you you
didn't want to face
like all of a sudden um things that were
like off about certain situations and so
on
and you were in denial about because
your high level priors made it difficult
for you to perceive them
all of a sudden like become readable
they they propagate in the network
and like you know presumably that could
have like a lot of like therapeutic
benefits in a lot of circumstances
now ribose is cool and i think it
explains a lot
but i actually think it's uh
very narrow in in in in a sense it's
like
it's it's not going into the actually
super crazy insane stuff that does
happen on psychedelics i mean like
hyperbolic geometry of dmt experiences
type stuff
you know like world sheet bending and
and 3d hyperbolic spaces
and um uh hyperbolic resonant modes and
you know space groups appearing in your
in your visual field
like there's a lot of stuff that like
reduced
you know beliefs under psychedelics they
don't touch you know that's not like
what
they're trying to explain you know but
maybe
if we pay attention to those you know
crazy aspects of psychedelics
maybe we can still apply the free energy
principle and get
some good insights which is what i'm
about to do
i'll i'll mention i guess about rebus a
a couple final things which is that
um there's also this kind of fun
commentary and great paper by
uh adam saffron uh called the sibus
which is like strengths
uh beliefs under psychedelics and
basically yeah he makes the
the point that like actually a lot of
things that happen on psychedelics are
more kind of towards the strengthening
of beliefs
as opposed to weakening of beliefs and
like a lot of you know like side effects
of psychedelics is like believing weird
stuff
so what's going on there and like he
kind of like talks about like
you know maybe yes psychologies do
weaken kind of this
uh or in a sense sensitize you know top
level priors
uh to prediction errors but also they
may strengthen like
medium level priors and that might give
rise to kind of like particular
hallucinations and expectations about
the input that
okay like maybe um uh you know the deep
dream of paradigm that like
this is something that kind of looks
like a dog all of a sudden congeals into
a dog so
that kind of feels like you're imposing
your high level model into the world
right so it's
the rebus story doesn't make sense of
everything really
uh but it also doesn't seem very
parsimonious to say like rebus and then
also cebus
but like so like the way like there's
kind of these competing forces and maybe
the story is pretty complicated
um i would also point to people to kind
of anil seth's lab and and the work of
michael sharpener uh scharther
uh i don't know how to pronounce his
surname apologies uh but yeah they're
doing like fascinating work and
basically
creating biologically plausible neural
network architectures
and then kind of disrupting them and
using generative models that come from
them
and they get essentially crazy things
like kind of a generalized
and more biologically plausible version
of deep dream
uh and i think that's fascinating
research and it's great uh and again
you know the literature is still waiting
for kind of a grand unification that
makes sense of rebus and cebus
and you know these like predictive
coding paradigms and and so on
but you know
like for a theory to be adequate it
actually
uh you know there's this criteria of
evidential uh
um uh adequacy
meaning that not only do you need to
explain
you know the deep dream effects on
psychedelics and you know the
updates of beliefs that you experience
you also need to explain machine elves
you also need to explain like tracer
phenomenology and enhance the valence
and the crazy harmony that happens in
some of those states and the annealing
effects and
and the dissolution of the self into the
rest of the cosmos and resonance between
people
there's a ton to explain i mean it's
very similar to
how like some theories of consciousness
uh for example claim to have an answer
you know to consciousness and yet if you
read into them you recognize
that they're not even addressing the
real problem of consciousness which is
you know any scientific theory of
consciousness
must be able to explain a the existence
of consciousness
b the causal properties of consciousness
why was it recruited by natural
selection you know
see the binding problem how is it
possible that we experience unified
moments of experience even though
neurons are
spatially distributed you know and and
see it must be able to explain
the full range of qualia patterns what
is the periodic table of possible qualia
values and patterns and the way in which
they can be interrelated with one
another what patterns can be bound with
one another
all of that all of that you need to
explain all of that
and as far as i can tell well rebus
definitely doesn't go that far
the free energy principle if you have a
certain mind and in particular if you're
very dismissive of like qualia or
something like that
i think you can kind of squint really
hard
and kind of you know get a glimpse
of the free energy principle as a theory
of consciousness
if you squint really hard the free
energy principle looks like a theory of
consciousness
i would claim no it's a theory of
dynamic systems
it's not addressing consciousness
directly but
given that a conscious system is a
dynamic system
you will be seeing a lot of free energy
principal
um uh effects happen in a conscious
system
i hope that that difference makes sense
it's uh very tricky what i just said
so i'm not saying you can explain
consciousness with the free energy
principle you can't
you know free energy principle is not a
theory of consciousness
but because consciousness is a complex
dynamic system
you will be able to find free energy
principle
appear in it all over the place
okay so it's kind of like flipping it
you know 180 degrees in a sense
while still highly valuing the free
energy principle
it's just very important to note it's
not a theory of consciousness okay i'm
repeating myself
let's get into the three super cool new
applications of the free energy
principle
to consciousness excuse me one second
so
first of all the free energy principle
is a computational theory
it's you know it's dealing with
probabilistic graphical models it's
something very natural in machine
learning it's not a
theory of physics although it's trying
to connect those principles with physics
um what we're doing at qri is actually
getting an
implementation level account of what the
brain is doing
and based on that implementation
inferring what kind of algorithms
can exist and in that sense you know the
computational level account that i was
describing
uh you know patient brain and so on
those are hard constraints
on the computational side we're
exploring the implementation level
and they will meet in the middle which
is like given the implementation
what algorithms are possible and likely
and given the computational side
basically what algorithms are necessary
so
with that it's kind of you know forward
chaining and back chaining and hopefully
we get a good insight in the middle so
i'll explain that in a second
so we model a
moment of experience as a resonance
network
and again this is not a full theory of
consciousness as i explained
but it does address in particular the
binding problem
at least at a functional level that when
you have a resonance network
um where basically each of the nodes
is a a metronome it could be a
more than one dimension metronome so
basically it could be for example like a
a square that has like various
vibrational modes
and in that way uh basically resonance
uh can be transitive in the sense of
like locking the system into a coherent
state
but the frequencies of resonance don't
need to be transitive between the nodes
so like
if node a is in resonance with b and b's
in c a and c don't need to be in
resonance with one another
they're only in a sense implicitly
influencing each other by their
influence on c
on b but on their own in a sense they
are not intrinsically in resonance with
one another so
there's kind of yeah this fascinating
aspect of the non-transitivity of this
uh resonance
of the frequencies of resonance and what
we're claiming
is that what the brain is fundamentally
doing is trying to minimize
dissonance now
from that i would claim we can derive
the free energy principle uh
as kind of an implication of this
implementation and again
it's not that the free energy principle
is you know fundamentally explaining
that you know how consciousness is
working here rather
is that this particular implementation
naturally gives rise
to a free energy uh reading and and and
uh this is as follows
so essentially um
in this system uh the
layers of the system basically when they
are
in dissonance with one another that will
encode a prediction error
that in a sense to make an accurate
prediction
entails that one layer can essentially
synchronize with the components of the
layer below and that
when that doesn't happen and in a sense
a layer is kind of like propagating
information that
the addition the further higher layer is
not predicting
that like that will generate an out of
phase interaction and that would be an
instance of dissonance
okay so that's one one component and
second
there might be an inherent complexity
cost
when you have a very complex model in
that complex models tend to give rise
to dissonance because there's a lot of
interrelationships
so in a sense in the balance
you know of trying to minimize
dissonance that gives rise to a balance
between
model complexity and prediction errors
and of course like the the the weight on
either it could be a kind of
something programmable like maybe by
genetics or like the the particular
particular details of the resonance
network but the point is that some of
those configurations will be very
adaptive
because they will hit precisely that
balance of in a sense
minimizing the the range of internal
possible states and
minimizing that entropy while at the
same time
minimizing the entropy that you know
comes from the environment because
it's making correct predictions and of
course this would happen also
recursively in each of the layers
uh each of the concentric shells of the
markov blanket so to speak
and uh the the fascinating thing here is
that
we can in a sense interpret something
like annealing neural annealing the the
paradigm we've talked about mike johnson
has an article about it
as a way of getting out of a
local minima of dissonance
that you're kind of like stuck in a
given configuration well with neural
annealing essentially you inject a ton
of energy
into the system and the systems in that
elevated higher energy state basically
the barrier
for uh exploring different states goes
down in a sense it's kind of like
weakens the constraints
and it allows us to basically uh as it
cools down to settle in a
much less dissonant configuration and as
a consequence
that process might give rise to actually
just generally better predictions about
the environment it doesn't necessarily
you know not always because it could
anneal something that is just too simple
you know like maybe with the wrong dose
in the wrong sentence setting
it may anneal something that is just way
too simple and for example something
like 5m or dmt
may just generate like such levels of
hyper coherence global hyper coherence
that
all the information gets lost and
basically super symmetrical state
basically you anneal to a model of the
world where
the expected thing is actually kind of
the dark room is basically this
infinite void and of course the infinite
void the first time you experienced it
is
incredibly surprising but the more
you experience the infinite void the
more natural
it feels the more kind of ground bait
you know basement reality type of
experience
but you can you can read it as
essentially like an annealing process
that is updating your bottle of the
world
such that like now minimizing free
energy requires you to take into account
the existence of the void
right anyway that's that's a cool cool
lens here uh
whereas you know in kind of the ribose
paradigm
annealing and they talk about annealing
a simulated annealing
has much more to do with things such as
like message passing
and uh um and belief propagation uh as
kind of like algorithms in probabilistic
graphical models
that in a sense when you weaken the
constraints there you can get an
annealing effect and as you strengthen
the constraints again
uh you may end up actually with a more
accurate model
now uh in a in a recent talk uh the
oxford uh
psychedelic society uh i basically
hypothesized and this also comes from uh
some conversations with uh
uh enrique bogorquez uh uh a volunteer
at qri
that yeah basically there might be a
very deep duality here
between actually what is happening in
the resonance network and what is
happening
in the belief network and that for
example
uh when you experience information you
don't like
it literally feels dissonant like
literally cognitive dissonance would be
actual physical dissonance going on in
the brain
and we're actually interested at qri to
test this and we think it's
feasible to actually to actually you
know publish a paper about like
cognitive dissonance
is physiological dissonance um
yeah and uh and also you know like
resisting information
uh kind of has this embodied you know
component that you're kind of like
in a sense like preventing the
information from propagating
and for example practices of equanimity
where you like learn to relax deeply and
just embrace whatever happens
in a sense what you're doing there it's
uh you're also because of the duality
you're allowing information to propagate
you're
not being in denial so to speak so
basically
yeah patterns of ten even muscular
tension would basically have
implications in how you're dealing with
information in the belief network
so anyway this is a super rich super
rich connection here
so that's number one of the free energy
principle and psychedelics qri themed
connections
the the second one is well this comes
from
yeah basically uh it's kind of a
synthesis
of uh mike's uh symmetry theory of
homostatic
regulation and the hyperbolic geometry
of dmt experiences so
uh i'll explain first yeah basically uh
mike hypothesizes that in a sense like
very symmetrical
you know harmonics in the nervous system
are kind of signals of health
because that in a sense allows you to do
very quick diagnosis in a sense
whenever there is symmetry breaking that
usually
will suggest or indicate there is damage
and you may not be able to kind of like
sequentially examine every aspect you
know every part of your body and compare
it with an inner template like that
might be computationally intractable
but detecting deviations from symmetry
might be very straightforward
in sort of kind of like a four-year
analysis uh
uh decomposition like you take the you
know how harmonious
the the the fourier analysis version the
fourier
analysis is and that will tell you
basically how symmetrical the state is
uh how much is deviating from its
homeostasis and so that's a super deep
idea and in a sense it's kind of like
algorithmic level account
that can be hooked up to the free energy
principle and makes a lot of sense
um and then there's also in the in the
hyperbolic geometry of dmt experiences
i talked about how dmt energizes
literally energizes your experience and
basically the way in which
energy and here are talking about
physical energy of course with kind of
like panzerkist
uh background assumption that actually
you know fields of
physics or fields of qualia which you
don't need to buy into for this to make
sense you could also talk about
total energy as maybe kind of average
neural activity or like intensity of
electric potential or something like
that
but yeah basically um what happens is
that on dmt
you have higher energy experiences and
this manifests
as very very bright colors or very
curved
world sheet basically the depth map of
your experience can become very very
very curved
it could also be felt in the form of
super intense high-energy resonance
or for example uh even even something
like
a very loud sound and basically on dmt
what will be happening is that the
energy is going to be chaotically
transitioning from one modality to
another and sometimes it may concentrate
i mean like there are
reports of people saying like yeah and
then all of a sudden the energy
concentrated in my visual field and i
experienced the most intense
blue i could possibly experience ever
and like okay yeah that's one solution
one high energy configuration for the
most part
most of the aspects of a dmt experience
is going to be kind of a
the energy distributed across a bunch of
modalities um
and and in addition
i talked about kind of bayesian energy
sinks you can look it up you know 2016
hyperbolic geometry of dmt experiences
article where i said that basically
what you recognize
lowers the energy so basically you have
like this chaotic kind of like
crazy patterns and then you know excited
world sheet
and then you kind of like see the corner
of a table and that kind of like
becomes a nucleation factor nucleation
point that basically propagates
the shape of the table and it condenses
and is in a sense kind of a
um yeah there's kind of condensation of
this excited world sheet
into a semantically meaningful shape
and and as a result the things that
actually survive
in a dmt state are in a sense the things
that are the highest likelihood
the things that i mean given how crazy
that is is like
what could possibly make make this sense
and uh and yes i mean that will be
importing a lot of stuff like narrative
information from previous trips what you
have read online like
you know alan watts and terence mckenna
all of that
will be kind of these like high-level
priors that will give rise to
condensations of the world
and of course that is a large extent why
i think there's a lot of
a ton of confirmation bias on on dmt
because essentially
what you have learned and what you what
you can recognize will condensate
as a world but you know it's a
fabrication i would claim it's a
fabrication
you're you're kind of subliminally
choosing it
because you can also condensate
something different
but uh but it's sometimes difficult to
resist
because like this and plus there's kind
of a uh
a momentum like they have like a
momentum of their own like
interpretations on dmt kind of gather
energy and
they're very difficult to stop once they
get started which is
yeah why i think it's very important to
basically develop a very very very good
aesthetic
very high level philosophical aesthetic
such that
basically the the things that you
recognize in the world are actually
beautiful things
and uh you know cooperate cooperate
equilibria between the sub-agents of
your experience
but uh uh to to kind of like synthesize
you know bayesian energy sinks with a
symmetry theory of homostatic regulation
essentially very similar to a soap
bubble the other thing that essentially
condenses the energy of the world sheet
is
symmetrical configurations so basically
in a super bubble
um basically any configuration besides
this perfectly spherical one
in a sense has potential energy and if
it has potential energy that immediately
translates
into kinetic energy makes the ball
essentially kind of like bounce
bounce off and because it's bouncing off
it's interfacing with
the gases around it and radiating
its energy so in a sense a soap bubble
radiates its energy until it reaches
its local minima of energy which in this
case is actually the global medium of
energy for that particular shape
which is perfect symmetrical spherical
configuration
likewise on dmt the shapes
that you experience will be local minima
of energy because they will be radiating
energy
to the environment and yeah i mean this
has to do with the holistic field
behavior and the fact that
literally the phenomenal objects in your
experience uh actually
kind of radiate uh waves of energy and
that that's a topic for another topic
i don't mean waves of energy from you
know outside kind of reaching
at you it's all in your world model like
there's a a kind of a
internally in your own experience your
world simulation
there's waves of energy that the objects
radiate and there's a lot of
super deep stuff about that but
basically
on dmt objects will do that they will
radiate their energy and so they will
condense
into their lowest energy configurations
with for for the most part will
bring up elements of symmetry and
that said the typical dmt experience is
going to be a hybrid of the two
is essentially going to be something
that simultaneously
has a lot of symmetries and it has
recognizable semantic content
because like that just happened to be
the way in which energy physical energy
was being minimized but you see like
this is so
deep and so awesome because with these
we have a
direct way of linking the free energy
principle which is a computational level
account
with physical energy minimization
as an algorithm in order to minimize
prediction errors while also
having good model complexity and this is
at the implementation level
so we're starting to get at kind of like
a big picture
that has answers to all of the levels of
analysis of mars levels of analysis
and i i don't know it makes me very
happy it's basically
the aim of qri is to have a full stack
theory of consciousness basically all of
the levels of analysis
and also you know a neuroscience
philosophy of mind and
neurotechnology and uh and i think like
yeah this kind of deep connections
is is the way forward okay so and i
promised you
that i would explain indra's net with
the free energy principle on on
psychedelics and meditation
so that's what i will conclude this
video with
uh so bear with me so
you've got to remember uh in in previous
videos i've talked about how
uh dmt one way you can model it
is as competing patterns of coherence
and in a sense uh this gives rise to an
evolutionary
uh process where like uh do you know
like our place
like reddit this is freddie.com place
was basically these like one million by
one million canvas
where yeah people were able to put a a
pixel every i don't know 10 minutes or
something like that
uh so like obviously you needed to
collaborate with others in order to
actually paint the
the whole thing and the dynamics that
emerged was were really cool right it's
like oh like some people were like in
the
low entropy let's make everything black
so let's make everything white
kind of a camp and others were like no
let's make a pikachu
let's make the the flag of uh australia
or
you know whatever it may be uh but the
point is that yeah there's kind of like
this competition
uh of like patterns and like basically
they're stronger one goes
the the more it can signal the more
visible it becomes the more people it
can attract
so basically there's kind of this like
the reach gets richer type of dynamics
as well
uh and then therefore kind of like a
power law distribution of like
how popular different patterns are well
the same on dmt
essentially one frame uh with which to
analyze dmt
is that this competing patterns of
coherence
is kind of like filling up your
experience by
basically the contents of your
subconscious what your subconscious can
recognize
and it's what it finds like emotionally
salient and
also kind of like mixing in like the
affordances of like highly symmetrical
configurations being like energy
minimizing configurations
so yeah in a sense like the crazy stuff
you see on dmt are
basically the balance between like the
forces
of the competing clusters of coherence
and sometimes
a cluster of coherence can win i mean it
can be like really
savvy at basically minimizing its free
energy and uh
and when he does that you know sometimes
you may have kind of like an alien
contact experience so where
the whole trip is kind of like you're
standing right next to like a lady or
like
you know a a mantis or something and
it's uh scolding you for something you
did or it's praising you or
telling you you're going to be the king
of the universe or
whatever it may be but basically it's
like telling you a story that is very
captivating and
being captivating and being consistent
with what you know
is one of the things that this you know
quasi-entity you know emergent you know
phenomena that happens on tmd that's how
they they get you you know that's how
they they attract your attention they
basically uh
build the things that simplify your
model of the world or make things make
sense
um and that is like very alluring you
know there's like this feeling of super
intelligence and yes
a dmt state is in some sense uh super
intelligence
in in some sense because it is finding
at an extremely fast pace connections
that you weren't able to find before
and and uh that could be computationally
very meaningful
at the same time because of the chaotic
nature of the state
and the coherence across the layers of
the hierarchy there's a lot of
forced belief updates so unfortunately
when you do experience kind of these dmt
beings
they kind of like force you to update
your beliefs towards
them being like real outside of your
existence and you can
like once you understand everything i've
talked to you about you
you will be able to notice this that
basically the way in which that
manifests
is as literal dissonance
that like if you rebel against the
updates
that uh dnt machine elf is uh giving you
um that will feel difficult it will
be like resisting and that resistance
will lead to dissonance it's going to be
unpleasant
which is why i think it's so important
to from the very beginning
of the dmt experience always hold
the you know upmost most
elevated aesthetic that you have such
that the
evolutionary selection pressures for the
patterns give rise to
kind of cooperate cooperate equilibria
and when that happens
that gonna give rise to indra's net
and what is interest net here okay so
we're coming to a close
everything everything is kind of like
munching together in order to get to
this
core insight i'm about to deliver to you
which is that the competing clusters of
coherence
in order for them to be good at
surviving
they must be able to model their
environment
and also they must be as simple as they
can be
so that there's not uh basically chaotic
elements within them that will
destabilize them and you know
shake themselves apart so to speak so
now imagine that like the entire field
of experience
is kind of like following these
principles following this gradient
and that they are more or less similar
and consonant with each other
so when you have those conditions and
you can
maximize the probability of those
conditions by you know taking dmt in a
really good state of mind and
holding a really good aesthetic in place
what will happen is that each of the
competing clusters of coherence
will generate a model
of their environment such that when they
receive kind of the waves of energy so
to speak
that they can match them with internal
waves of energy simultaneously
that will reinforce the specific pattern
that they
are and as a consequence
and because in a sense like fractality
and cell similarity is also one way of
like minimizing complexity
what can literally happen is that you
will have these
groups competing patterns of coherence
that each of them literally contains a
tiny reflection
but every other one uh scaled downwards
so that like
basically kind of like corresponds to
the appropriate scale
and within each of them you will have a
smaller one now it's not going to go
infinitely
there's no space plus you know the
frequencies are not
infinite freq you know the frequency has
a a maximum value
so like the the bands of the waves of
energy as they they radiate
and so they they cannot be like
infinitely thin
so there's not infinite complexity but
there can be several layers
of like mutual modeling
and uh because the simplest
configuration is going to be
essentially when all of the competing
clusters of coherence are identical
when you have the conditions set up
right basically the gradient
moves towards literally every
cluster of coherence being a sort of
fractal reflection of every other
cluster of coherence
and that way they can predict each other
perfectly and they don't
they don't lose their shape they
minimize energy
they make perfect predictions they're a
completely stable state
and it's high valence because it's all
consonant
and that's interest net
so hopefully hopefully you got some of
that if not
i'm sure we'll talk about this another
time and um
i'm sure you can re-watch the video a
later stage
maybe after taking dmt and experiencing
these and
you know you'll see what i mean uh but
anyway i just i was just very excited to
share all of these
so uh i think like to to conclude you
know
this is the sort of conversation that i
really think um
you know there really should be a place
in the world for it to exist and i think
uh
qri has a really good chance of being
that place we're basically
uh constructing the infrastructure and
yeah basically
we're going to make hires later this
year
so and we're aiming for yeah basically
like
super smart people uh very value aligned
and uh you know if all of this interests
you if you have the mathematical
background and
uh you have like strong technical skills
and uh
you love philosophy yes i mean please
read
all of our stuff you know maybe in six
months uh we might hire you
i've gotta be honest though there's
gonna be a very high bar
but i don't know in six months maybe you
can get there
either way though um this is a a big
movement
and a and a larger community so
whether you know you're working directly
on these projects or not you can you can
tag along
and write blog posts make videos and yes
essentially make
consciousness research super cool uh
that's that's the goal
and uh and reduce suffering massively as
a consequence
so with that thank you so much infinite
please and i'll talk to you
another time take care have a wonderful
wonderful time